Hello, and welcome back to another episode
of ItsDrDan, and this time we're going
to be going through electronegativity and
polarity, which can be one of the more
confusing concepts for a lot of students
when it comes to chemical bonding.
So when you learned about this picture of
bonding, there's two major types of bonds.
There's ionic, which was all about
giving and receiving electrons, and
then there was covalent bonding, which
was about the sharing of electrons.
However, one thing that you probably
found out in your chemistry class is
that covalent isn't always this Equal
sharing of electrons that a lot of times
it's about this Sometimes it's not always
even if you've ever split something
with somebody that you might have liked
Maybe they took a few more or something.
Maybe it was even it's not always the
case So let's learn about this periodic
trend and we'll go through some examples
analogies of what this looks like so You
might have seen the electronegativity
chart, something like this, where it's
showing the periodic table and all of
a sudden there's all these different
numbers and values, and what this is
reflecting is that different atoms
tend to be a little more greedy when
it comes to electrons, and it has to do
with their valence electron levels, so
something like fluorine, for example,
That has 7 valence electrons, oxygen has
6, nitrogen has 5, carbon has 4 valence
electrons in that outermost layer.
So fluorine, it really
wants to get that octet.
It's willing to do whatever it
can to get that last electron.
And because of that, it's going to
lead to uneven sharing across covalent
bonds between Different atoms.
So what we see here is in this trend
is that there is an unevenness towards
the top right of the periodic table.
So electro negativity is going up into
the right, and this trend is following
the same thing that ionization energy.
Meaning that these electrons,
these atoms are not willing
to give up their electrons.
In fact, they're, they're on
the border of becoming ionic is
how much this uneven sharing is.
So let's...
Look, let's look at that and try
to understand this trend and see
if we can, how will it be applied.
So, most of this has to do with bonds.
In fact, polar covalent bonds.
And what this looks like is, it's
very similar to a tug of war, or
almost like you're on a seesaw
between two different atoms.
So I have a few little images here just to
kind of illustrate what this looks like.
So the first one is
between carbon and carbon.
the same atoms.
So what would that look like?
Well, being that they are the
same atom, they're going to have
the same amount of pull on each
other across the covalent bond.
And we can prove this with
electronegativity values.
So if I look at this chart, we can see
that we have for carbon a value of 2.
5.
So what can we do with that, with that?
Well, we can try to
figure out the difference.
So if 2.
5 is for one carbon, 2.
5 is for the other.
Well, what is the difference between them?
Well, we can do some little simple math
where we take the bigger value, even
though they're the same, subtracted
by the smaller one, and we see that,
oh, when we subtract them, it's zero.
So what that tells you is
that we can go to a chart.
And see that, oh, there are labels for
what that difference is between them.
So being that this is less than 0.5,
this is a nonpolar covalent bond.
Meaning that it's an even sharing.
So it's something that's, you
don't see more electrons going
towards one side versus the other.
So what does that look
like in terms of orbitals?
Well, if I have these two carbons that are
bound to each other, and I draw a little
electron cloud around them, it's going
to be a nice, even, type of distribution
of electrons across that cloud.
So it's nice and happy.
It's nice and nonpolar.
So this is exactly what these
different species sort of want.
They want to try to be
nonpolar if possible.
So, and that's what we're seeing here.
Now, what about carbon and oxygen?
Well, we know that the value It's 2.5.
Now what about oxygen?
Well, once again, you can probably
take a guess based on the image Is
that the the girl on the right is kind
of taking more of the milk electron
milkshake than the guy on the left?
And that's because the trend is
it's going up and to the right so,
you know oxygen is more polar So 3.
5 Which is a lot higher, so what we
can show for ourselves to prove it, is
we take the bigger value, which is 3.
5, and subtract it by
the smaller value, so 2.
5, and what we will get
is a difference of 1.
0.
So, What that tells you is like, all
right, if we look at our chart again, is
that falls right into the polar covalent
area, meaning it's uneven and most of
it is going towards oxygen in this case.
So, whenever we have something that
is polar covalent, the way that I
like to always use the analogy is if
you've ever gone to Out probably with
a significant other or friend and you
ever decided to maybe split fries or a
dessert or something Probably a lot of
the times like maybe you might have had
it even where you're each like cutting
it down the middle You're sharing it
and that's really great However, some
people might want a few more fries than
the other one when they're not looking
and then all of a sudden It's uneven.
So and that's just how life
can be sometimes So with that
we control that draw that too.
So if I have carbon And oxygen, well,
this means that the cloud is going
to be more on Oxygen, because that
has a higher electronegativity value.
So when we show that, it's gonna be more
like, little, little bit more teardrop
shaped, and more of the electrons,
or the shading, which represents
the electrons, shading, electrons.
So it's gonna be a little more
towards oxygen, in this case.
So it's gonna be more heavily favored.
Now, With fluorine, the last example,
it's just like if you're sharing with
a little kid and they're taking the
milkshake, they're obviously going
to want all of it, so you're going
to see a very uneven side of this.
So fluorine has the highest
value possible, which is a 4.
0.
Carbon has, once again, has a 2.
5.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to subtract those two values.
So 4.
0 minus 2.
5.
And that's a 1.
5 difference.
So it's really, really polar
and in favor of fluorine.
So when we have that, how that's going
to look, it's going to look very similar
to the carbon oxygen picture, but another
way to illustrate that for everybody
that might be struggling to understand
this, it's very similar to a seesaw or
a teeter totter, where if I have carbon
on one side, and fluorine on the other,
and this is my electron balance, well,
we're going to have more of the electrons
on the fluorine side in this case.
So it's going to be very, very uneven.
So, and what we can do with that
is there's ways to label this and
understand it a little bit further.
So this picture is very much like
this one that I have here where
I have a chlorine who has a 3.
0 value.
You know it's more up and right to
the periodic table as well, so it
goes on the trend versus hydrogen.
It's pulling or tugging all
of those electrons towards it.
So as a result, it's something
where it's very, very uneven.
Hydrogen just wants to share its
electron, but it's like, here you can
have it, but it's pulling it away.
So it's making it extremely
polar as a result.
So, how do we illustrate this on bonds?
So if I use, let's say, the
picture above, the HCl, how can we
show that for hydrochloric acid?
So with this one, what we're going to
be using is a couple different symbols.
The first one is delta symbols, which
look like, almost like little music notes.
So with this, so this is a
delta, So Greek letter delta
and this shows partial charges.
So keep in mind this
is not an ionic charge.
So for this it's very similar to
like magnets where there's a little
bit of attraction between magnets.
But you can still pull them apart.
So with this one, the way
that we would label it is we
would look at the two values.
So chlorine was a 3.
0, hydrogen is a 2.
1.
So, we can label chlorine as a
delta negative and hydrogen as a
delta plus, telling you that the
charge is slightly more on chlorine.
It's uneven, okay?
Another way for you to show this
as well is using arrow notation.
So, let's say if I take HF, for example.
So fluorine earlier had a value of 4.
0, hydrogen has a value of 2.
1.
So for this one, there's another
notation which uses arrow notation.
So what this arrow represents is
something referred to as a dipole.
So all these differences in charge,
so the difference in partial charge
is a dipole.
Okay, so that's what that
refers to, or a dipole moment.
So whenever a molecule has a dipole
moment, this creates polarity.
So the way we can show this, we can
use the deltas from before, or We
can use a plus on the hydrogen, but
remember this is a partial positive.
So we then create an arrow
pointing towards the fluorine.
So this tells you that, okay, hydrogen has
a little less electrons, but it's getting
Pulled towards the fluorine, and that's
why the arrow is going towards that.
Okay, so this allows us to be able
to illustrate polar bonds by creating
permanent dipoles, which is going
to be a very important concept For
the future, when you start looking
at intermolecular forces and trying
to determine polar molecules.
Okay, so, now the biggest important
thing to keep in mind is, is
this how you illustrate them?
But you're going to be going
off your periodic trend.
So remember, the farther you go up and
to the right of that periodic table,
the more electronegative an atom is.
So that's how you can kind of
tell if something is polar.
The closer is the fluorine.
And the farther, the farther
they are away from each other,
the more polar they will be.
This is Dr.
Dan for this time.
I hope this video helped, and please come
in and tune in for my next video, which
will be on part two, which goes over the
difference between a polar bond, which
is what we talked about in this video.
and polar molecules, which
is putting it all together.
Alright, if you like this video,
please consider liking and subscribing,
and I hope to see you next time.
Thank you so much.
Bye.
Have a wonderful day.